A Guide to the William W. Abbot Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William W. Abbot Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12805
ca. 8150 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply to personally identifiable student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisitions
The collection was a gift to the University of Virginia Library from William W. Abbot on April 17, 1992
Biographical/Historical Information
William W. Abbot (1922-2009) a native of Louisville, Georgia and a long time resident of Virginia was an admired and world famous historian, professor, scholar, administrator, and editor. His career spanned nearly fifty years and he was described as a "man of letters," and an editor of great skill, knowledge, and tact. Colleagues also described him as possessing "gentlemanly good humor and decent human concern, much valued during his stints as chairman." He was also known for his "acts of personal and professional generosity." He changed many lives by offering his support to graduate students, working in their best interests to improve their writing and find respectable history positions for them throughout the country.
He was the chief editor of the Papers of George Washington and an expert in early American History. He attended Davidson College and graduated from the University of Georgia in 1943, whereupon he entered the United States Navy. Using the G. I. Bill, he earned his master's and doctoral degrees in history from Duke University in 1953. He taught at William and Mary from 1953 to 1962; Northwestern University 1958-1959; Rice University 1962 and returned to William and Mary from 1963 to 1966. He edited the William and Mary Quarterly from 1961 to 1966 and the Journal of Southern History from 1960 to 1961. He was among the founders of the Association for Documentary Editing. In 1966 he was recruited by the University of Virginia to be the James Madison Professor of History. In addition to teaching and editing, he served twice as the chairman of the Corcoran Department of History at the University of Virginia.
He retired from the University of Virginia in 1992, although he continued to edit individual volumes of the Washington Papers until 1998, when nearly fifty volumes were in print. He was the author of two books, "The Royal Governors of Georgia, 1754-1775," and "The Colonial Origins of the United States, 1607-1763," and a number of articles.
He was president of the Alpha chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, served on the councils of the Institute of Early American History and Culture and the Southern Historical Association. For twenty years, he was on the board of editors of The Virginia Quarterly Review, was a member of the Gridiron Club at the University of Georgia and the University of Virginia's honorary Raven Society.
The College of William and Mary awarded him the honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters in 1998, and the Virginia Historical Society made him a life member. He was best known for his work as chief editor of The Papers of George Washington (1977-1992). According to his son, Abbot believed that "his chief contribution as a teacher and historian came from the attentive reading and detailed responses that he gave over the years to the writing of his students and fellow historians." The personal and professional correspondence in this collection does indeed confirm that he spent much of his time reading and offering helpful advice to thousands of writers.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the professional, academic and personal papers of William W. Abbot, James Madison Professor of History and Editor of the Papers of George Washington at the University of Virginia. The collection is from 1953 to 1996 and is about 8,150 items, 26 hollinger boxes, and 10 linear feet. It consists of department and personal correspondence with historians, university colleagues, students, friends and academic organizations throughout the United States and around the world. There are also financial papers, lecture notes, reviews, speeches, organization records associated with Abbot's activities while at William and Mary and the University of Virginia, a typescript of his writing, "The Colonial Beginnings of the United States 1607-1763," and communications with publishers relating to books and articles he authored.
Correspondents include University of Virginia Presidents Edgar F. Shannon, Frank L. Hereford, Robert O'Neil, and John Casteen. Other University of Virginia correspondents include Melvin Leffler, David A.Shannon, Merrill D. Peterson, Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., Robert D. Cross, Fredson Bowers, and William Kelso.
There are also papers and correspondence of numerous organizations including the American Council of Learned Societies, Institute of Early American History and Culture, American Historical Association, American Studies Program at the University of Virginia, Atlas of Early American History, Association for Documentary Editing, Society of the Cincinnati, Conference on the Northwest Ordinance, fraternities, Georgia Historical Society, Journal of Southern History, Library of Virginia, Mississippi Valley Historical Association, Annual Stratford Hall Seminar, National Endowment for the Humanities, City University of New York, New-York Historical Society, Organization of American Historians, Potomac River Basin Consortium, Social Studies yearbook, the Southern Historical Association, the University of Virginia including the Faculty Senate, the Corcoran Department of History, the graduate committee, Arts and Sciences, the Public Occasions Committee, the University Press of Virginia, the Papers of George Washington, the Papers James Monroe, and the Papers of George Mason; the United States Navy, Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission, and information about other universities.
There are numerous materials that are confidential including recommendation letters, selection committee papers, information about promotions and salaries, the sesquicentennial committee, student papers, grades, and roll books.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic. Correspondence is in alphabetical order and can be found by surname and by the institute that the individual was associated. Confidential material is placed alphabetically by topic at the end of the collection.
Contents Listings
- 1964-1991 General Correspondence Abbot-Ayers, 64 items (Box-folder 1:1)
- 1966-1992 General Correspondence Backus-Bearrs, 108 items (Box-folder 1:2)
- 1965-1992 General Correspondence Bedford-Belk, 53 items (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1965-1992 General Correspondence Bell-Berwick, 38 items (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1953-1997 General Correspondence Bickford-Bowers, 69 items (Box-folder 1:5)
- 1967- 1990 General Correspondence Braden-Breslin, 52 items (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1963-1994 General Correspondence Brice-Byrd, 42 items (Box-folder 1:7)
- 1964-1997 General Correspondence Calabro-Chisholm, 45 items (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1964-1992 General Correspondence Cinncinnati-Cress, 57 items (Box-folder 2:2)
- 1962-1994 General Correspondence Criswold-Cutler, 82 items (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1963-1997 General Correspondence Dabney-Dickinson, 44 items (Box-folder 2:4)
- 1963-1992 General Correspondence Doebele-Dyer, 64 items (Box-folder 2:5)
- 1962-1997 General Correspondence East-Evett, 91 items (Box-folder 2:6)
- 1963-1991 General Correspondence Fairbanks-Furth, 86 items (Box-folder 2:7)
- 1963-1995 General Correspondence Galambos-Giunta, 54 items (Box-folder 3:1)
- 1962-1995 General Correspondence Godkin-Gwin, 82 items (Box-folder 3:2)
- 1962-1991 General Correspondence Hagen-Harris, 50 items (Box-folder 3:3)
- 1962-1990 General Correspondence Harrison-Hawley, 65 items (Box-folder 3:4)
- 1962-1991 General Correspondence Healy-Higginbottom, 55items (Box-folder 3:5)
- 1978-1996 General Correspondence Higgins-Hofstra, 67 items (Box-folder 3:6)
- 1966-1989 General Correspondence Holman-Hutson, 53 items (Box-folder 3:7)
- 1962-1991 General Correspondence Indiana-Justin, 76 items (Box-folder 4:1)
- 1966-1995 General Correspondence Kahtilhau-Kittle, 57 items (Box-folder 4:2)
- 1965-1995 General Correspondence Klein-Krasner, 43 items (Box-folder 4:3)
- 1967-1995 General Correspondence Krugler-Kurtz, 37 items (Box-folder 4:4)
- 1966-1989 General Correspondence Lackey-Lawson, 53 items (Box-folder 4:5)
- 1983-1996 General Correspondence Leach-Leffler, 27 items (Box-folder 4:6)
- 1962-1995 General Correspondence Leiberger-Lewis, 31 items (Box-folder 4:7)
- 1962-1996 General Correspondence Lightner-Lucas, 48 items (Box-folder 5:1)
- 1972-1995 General Correspondence McBride-McElroy, 35 items (Box-folder 5:2)
- 1980-1994 General Correspondence McGifferd-McPherson, 48 items (Box-folder 5:3)
- 1962-1996 General Correspondence Macy-Mississippi, 48 items (Box-folder 5:4)
- 1962-1996 General Correspondence Mitchell-Myers, 54 items (Box-folder 5:5)
- 1963-1997 General Correspondence Nagel-Parker, 80 items (Box-folder 5:6)
- 1962-1991 General Correspondence Pearre-Plaxco, 40 items (Box-folder 6:1)
- 1962-1992 General Correspondence Poirier-Pyron, 31 items (Box-folder 6:2)
- 1963-1997 General Correspondence Raags-Rist, 54 items (Box-folder 6:3)
- 1962-1997 General Correspondence Ritchie-Ryerson, 85 items (Box-folder 6:4)
- 1964-1992 General Correspondence Sabato-Settle, 57 items (Box-folder 6:5)
- 1965-1996 General Correspondence Shackelfort-Shy, 47 items (Box-folder 6:6)
- 1962-1993 General Correspondence Sikorsky-Spivak, 109 items (Box-folder 6:7)
- 1969-1993 General Correspondence Stagg-Symms, 56 items (Box-folder 7:1)
- 1965-1993 General Correspondence Taishoff-Thorp, 58 items (Box-folder 7:2)
- 1961-1992 General Correspondence Tinkler-Twobig, 34 items (Box-folder 7:3)
- 1958-1959 General Correspondence Towner and about Towner, 31 items (Box-folder 7:4)
- 1963-1995 General Correspondence Underdown-Votte, 53 items (Box-folder 7:5)
- 1962-1992 General Correspondence Wagoneer-Wheeler, 46 items (Box-folder 7:6)
- 1962-1995 General Correspondence White-Wyllie, 69 items (Box-folder 7:7)
- 1964-1996 General Correspondence Yancey-Zweig, 37 items (Box-folder 7:8)
- 1962-1996 Miscellaneous Correspondence, 94 items (Box-folder 7:9)
- 1970-1992(UVA) Presidents Correspondence, 16 items (Box-folder 7:10)
- 1971-1972 Publishing Correspondence-Cummin, 10 items (Box-folder 7:11)
- 1966-1981 Organizations Correspondence American Council of Learned Societies, 58 items (Box-folder 8:1)
- 1979-1986 American Council of Learned Societies: Committees on Scholarly Communication (ARL), 36 items (Box-folder 8:2)
- 1980-1981 American Historical Association Program Committee, 19 items (Box-folder 8:3)
- 1962 American Historical Association Session "The Function of the Colonial Executive in the 18 th Century", 17 items (Box-folder 8:4)
- 1970 American Historical Association Session, 6 items (Box-folder 8:5)
- 1967 American Historical Association and Omohundro Institute of Early American History & Culture Joint Sessions, 12 items (Box-folder 8:6)
- 1968 American Studies Program Gilbert Fite, 5 items (Box-folder 8:7)
- 1978-1984; 1990 Association for Documentary Editing, 27 items (Box-folder 8:8)
- 1970-1971 Atlas of Early American History, 4 items (Box-folder 8:9)
- 1973-1974 City University of New York Graduate History Program, 14 items (Box-folder 8:10)
- 1986 Nov 7-8 Conference Northern Virginia Studies, 8 items (Box-folder 8:11)
- 1986-1987 Conference- The Northwest Ordinance Sheehan, 21 items (Box-folder 8:12)
- 1986 Oct 16-19 Conference- Washington As Founder: Mount Vernon, 9 items (Box-folder 8:13)
- 1962-1986 Fraternity- Phi Alpha Theta, 8 items (Box-folder 9:1)
- 1984-1986 Fraternity- Phi Beta Kappa, 7 items (Box-folder 9:2)
- 1980 Commission on Fraternities and Sororities, 11 items (Box-folder 9:3)
- 1968-1969; 1980-1983 Georgia Historical Society, 41 items (Box-folder 9:4)
- 1962-1977 Institute of Early American History and Culture: American Revolution, 88 items (Box-folder 9:5)
  Correspondents include Lester J. Cappon, Elizabeth Suttell, James Morton Smith, Gordon S.Wood, Susan Lee Foard, Thad W. Tate, Stephen G. Kurtz, Richard "Dick" Maxwell Brown, James H. Hutson, Norman S. Fiering, and Michael McGiffert. There are also minutes from the annual meeting.
- 1978 Institute of Early American History and Culture, 40 items (Box-folder 9:6)
  Correspondents include Norman S. Fiering, Alfred F.Young, Mary Maples Dunn, Thad W. Tate, and Sydney V. James. There are letters from the Newberry Library. Included are book reviews from William and Mary and minutes from the Executive Meeting of the Council.
- 1979-1980 Institute of Early American History and Culture, 40 items (Box-folder 9:7)
  Thad W. Tate, Philip Greven, Sydney V. James, Alfred F.Young. There is information about the procedures for a Nominating Committee and a proposed budget report.
- 1962-1970 Journal of Southern History, 32 items (Box-folder 9:8)
  Correspondents include Lester J. Cappon, Elizabeth Suttell, Andrew Forest Muir, William H. Masterson, William H. "Bill" Nelson, and S. W. Higginbotham. There are also annual reports for the journal.
- 1969-1991 Miscellaneous conferences, 21 items (Box-folder 9:9)
- 1962; 1965 Mississippi Valley Historical Association, 25 items (Box-folder 9:10)
  Correspondents include Samuel P. Hays and William H. Masterson
- 1985 (Monticello) Stratford Hall Seminars, 6 items (Box-folder 9:11)
  Included are handwritten notes by Bill Abbot
- 1970-1972 National Council for the Social Studies, 10 items (Box-folder 10:1)
  Correspondents include Richard L. Watson, Jr., and William H. Cartwright who were editing a book that Mr. Abbot was writing about American History. Included are typescripts from the book
- 1980-1986 National Endowment for the Humanities, 18 items (Box-folder 10:2)
  Included are applications for grant proposals
- 1982 New-York State Historical Society, 9 items (Box-folder 10:3)
  There is correspondence from Milo V. Stewart about the Society and conferences it sponsored
- 1970-1971 Organization of American Historians, 10 items (Box-folder 10:4)
  Correspondents include Thomas D. Clark, R. Nicholas Olsberg, Jack P. Greene, about papers being submitted for conferences. Included is a paper by Richard Ryerson: The Institutional Response to Crisis Politics"
- 1976-1981 Organization of American Historians Prize Contest, 27 items (Box-folder 10:5)
  There is correspondence from Bennett H. Wall, John J. Rumbarger, Michael McGiffert, Richard S. Kirkendall, Richard G. Hewlett, Edward Pessen, Carl Parrini, and Thomas C. Holt about the Charles Thomson Prize Contest
- 1979-1984 Potomac River Basin Consortium, 67 items (Box-folder 10:6)
  Correspondents include David A. Shannon, Frank L. Hereford, Gilbert Gude, U.S. Senator Charles Mathias, Jr., Harvey H. Jackson, Edwin E. Floyd, Robert H. Hartman, and Paul C. Nagel
- 1978; 1987-1992 Society of the Cincinnati, 26 items (Box-folder 10:7)
  Correspondents include Martin Havran, Clifford Lewis, John Sanderson du Mont, H. Bartholomew Cox, Thad W. Tate, and Richard H. Beeman
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Bacote, 5 items (Box-folder 10:8)
  Correspondence from Clarence A. Bacote, Alonzo T. Stephens, Charles H. Wesley about which papers would be presented at the SHA Conference
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Critoph, 8 items (Box-folder 10:9)
  There is correspondence from Gerald E. Critoph who was organizing the sessions at the SHA Conference
- 1968 Southern Historical Association-Delzell, 8 items (Box-folder 10:10)
  Correspondence of Charles F. Delzell who was the organizer of the sessions at the SHA Conference
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Dew, 9 items (Box-folder 10:11)
  Included is the correspondence of SHA Conference organizer Charles Dew and Richard B. Sherman
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Donald, 10 items (Box-folder 10:12)
  Correspondence of David H. Donald who organized an SHA Conference
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Frantz, 7 items (Box-folder 10:13)
  Correspondence of Joe B. Frantz, chairman of joint conference with the American Association for State and Local History and the Southern Historical Association in 1968
- 1968 Southern Historical Association-Kurtz, 24 items (Box-folder 10:14)
  Included is the correspondence of Stephen G. Kurtz, one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Link, 2 items (Box-folder 10:15)
  Correspondence of Arthur S. Link, president of the SHA and one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-McPherson, 15 items (Box-folder 10:16)
  Correspondence of James McPherson, one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Shannon, 10 items (Box-folder 10:17)
  Correspondence of David Shannon, one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-TePaske, 8 items (Box-folder 10:18)
  Correspondence of Jack TePaske, one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Wall, 21 items (Box-folder 11:1)
  Correspondence of Bennett H. Wall, Secretary-Treasurer of the Southern Historical Association
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association-Woodward, 5 items (Box-folder 11:2)
  Correspondence of C. Vann Woodward, one of the organizers of the SHA Conference in New Orleans in 1968
- 1962-1984 Southern Historical Association, 24 items (Box-folder 11:3)
  Included is general correspondence about the 1968 SHA Conference in New Orleans and the 1971 SHA Conference in Houston. There is an SHA Annual Report (1970-1971) and the SHA's Fiftieth Anniversary Program in 1984. There are also scholarly papers by Martin H. Quitt ("From Elite to Aristocracy" and Warren M. Billings, "The Development of Political Institutions in Virginia, 1634-1676)
- 1977-1981 Southern Historical Association Executive Council, 19 items (Box-folder 11:4)
  Included are Professor Abbot's request to serve on the Executive Council for the SHA, reports for the November 1978 Executive Council meetings, and minutes for the December 3, 1980, January 20, 1981, and December 7, 1981 Executive Council meetings.
- 1976 Southern Historical Association Membership Committee, 14 items (Box-folder 11:5)
  Included is a progress report for new members in 1976 and correspondence concerning increasing SHA's membership.
- 1968 Southern Historical Association Program Abstracts, 42 items (Box-folder 11:6)
  Abstracts of papers to be discussed in sessions at the 1968 SHA Conference in New Orleans
- 1975-1977 Southern Historical Association Program Committee, 116 items (Box-folder 11:7)
  Correspondence and planning for the SHA Conference in New Orleans in November 1977 are included. Also contains the proposal selection process for the Conference sessions to be held
- 1968 Southern Historical Association Program Corrections, 49 items (Box-folder 11:8)
  Included are requests for corrections to the memorandum for the 1968 SHA Conference in New Orleans.
- 1968 Southern Historical Association Program Summary for Journal, 5 items (Box-folder 11:9)
  Contains a paper and edits summarizing what happened at the 1968 SHA Conference in New Orleans.
- 1967-1968 Southern Historical Association Programs, 33 items (Box-folder 11:10)
  There is a program of the sessions held, report of the Program Committee, memorandum, expenses, and general correspondence concerning the 1968 SHA Conference in New Orleans. Also included is correspondence from Sanford Higginbotham, Bennett Wall, Dumas Malone, and Neva Armstrong.
- 1982 Southern Historical Association Session, 2 items (Box-folder 12:1)
  Notes relating to Abbot's session for which he presided at the 1982 SHA Conference in Memphis
- 1968 Southern Historical Association Session Reports, 34 items (Box-folder 12:2)
  Brief reports of the sessions at the 1968 SHA Conference held in New Orleans
- 1980-1981 Southern Historical Association Committee on the Status of Women in the Profession, 15 items (Box-folder 12:3)
  There is correspondence on the new Committee on the Status of Women Historians in the Southern Historical Association. Also included is correspondence from Charles P. Roland, Carol Bleser, Jimmie Franklin, Paul Nagel, and Joseph Tregle.
- 1943-1961 US Navy, 32 items (Box-folder 12:4)
  Included is an an Honorable Discharge Certificate, Annual Qualifications Questionnaires, Officer's Qualification Reports, and an Appointment Acknowledgement to the permanent rank of Lieutenant.
- 1960-1961 Rice University-William and Mary Career Change, 19 items (Box-folder 12:5)
  Included is Abbot's appointment to associate professor at Rice University and correspondence relating to editing various reports and volumes for The Journal of Southern History.
- 1961-1963 Rice University-William and Mary Career Change, 46 items (Box-folder 12:6)
  Included is correspondence regarding the move back to Williamsburg, research project in South Carolina, and career switch to editor of the William and Mary Quarterly.
- 26 Sept 1977 University of Georgia Press, 1 item (Box-folder 12:7)
  Included is a letter thanking Professor Abbot for editing a paper by Harvey H. Jackson.
- 1968 University of New Hampshire, 24 items (Box-folder 12:8)
  Included is correspondence of the evaluation committee for the University of New Hampshire's proposed Ph.D. program in History and the written proposal.
- 1983 UVA Summer on the Lawn, 5 items (Box-folder 12:9)
  Includes an article about Abbot's "Summer on the Lawn" speech
- 1966-1986 UVA Arts and Sciences, 8 items (Box-folder 12:10)
  Includes a report on admissions for the 1965-1966 academic year, a list of new faculty members in 1966, correspondence relating to the various committees in which Abbot was involved including the Committee on Educational Policy and the Budget and the Thomas Jefferson Fellows Committee.
- 1968-1969 UVA Center for Textual and Editorial Studies, 17 items (Box-folder 12:11)
  Included are correspondence, notes, and a proposal for the founding of the Center. Also contains correspondence about searching for a director
- 1968-1973 UVA Committee on Educational Policy, 18 items (Box-folder 12:12)
  Included are notes about meetings and a report of the Committee on Educational Policy and the Budget. There are letters of gratitude from Weldon Cooper and Joseph H. McConnell for the committee's help on the nomination of Frank L. Hereford as the next President of the University.
- 1969 UVA Faculty Senate-Student Representation, 19 items (Box-folder 12:13)
  Includes the Report of Committee on student representatives at Faculty Meetings and notes relating to chairing and the meetings of this committee
- 1970-1971 UVA Faculty Senate-Procedures and Proposals, 39 items (Box-folder 12:14)
  Includes meeting minutes, nominations to Senate committees, the revised and proposed grievance procedures; new Senate Committee on Faculty Relations, the Report of a Special Committee on the University Senate, and proposals for programs in General Linguistics, Religious Studies, Accounting, and Biomedical Engineering.
- 1966-1991 UVA Faculty Senate, 24 items (Box-folder 13:1)
  Includes notes from the committee investigating the process for awarding degrees in the Graduate School of the Arts and Sciences, notes on a Center of Editorial and Textual Study, and meeting minutes of the Executive Council of the Faculty Senate. Also of note are papers concerning the Nomination Committee of the next University President, including a letter informing Abbot of his election to this committee.
- 1969-1971 UVA Faculty Senate- Meetings, 26 items (Box-folder 13:2)